A Guide to the IAWA Small Collections, 1907-2013
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
- Persons and Associations
  - Moody, Harriet and Mildred Moody [Moody Sisters], report, 2000, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 6)
    Report from Santa Barbara's Historic Landmarks Commission on securing a landmark designation for 1086 Coast Village Road, A Moody Sisters design. The report contains biographical information about the sisters and history about their architectural business.
  - Muller, Cornelia, papers, 1983-1988, Extent: 0.2 cubic feet (Box 6, Box 11)
    Architect of Berlin, Germany, and a partner in the firm Muller, Knippschild, Wehberg. Materials consist of photographs (1983-1988) of her work with her firm, biographical information, and a brochure of her designs.
  - Muller-Schmid, Catherine, papers, 1987-1988 and undated, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 6)
    Born 1953. Architect of Zurich, Switzerland. Materials include a résumé and forty-five copies of photographs and architectural drawings of apartment complexes and other residential housing projects she has designed.
  - Muntoni, Alessandra, papers, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 6)
    Practicing architect in Rome, Italy. Muntoni is a founder and co-editor of the journal metamorfosi: quaderni di architettura Papers consist of a résumé, a brochure of works completed, and editorials published in the magazine metamorfosi (no.48 Jan.-Mar. 2004 and no. 52 Jan.-Feb. 2005). Her 2003 book, Metamorph: Architetture = Works and Projects 1965-2003: Gabriele De Giorgi, Alessandra Muntoni, Marcello Pazzaglini is cataloged in ADDISON and available in the Special Collections Rare Book Room.
  - Nakahara, Nobuko, exhibit boards, 2002, Extent: 2.0 cubic feet (Oversize 2)
    1929-2008. Architect of Japan. Nakahara received her architecture degree from the Musashi Institute of Technology (now Tokyo City University) in 1952. She was also involved on the international scene serving as Vice President of International Union of Women Architects (UIFA) and as president and president emeritus of UIFA JAPON. Her collection contains copies of boards made for the exhibition "Women and Architecture - creating better housing and cities/towns for supporting both work and family life." Exhibition was held at the "Center for Advancement of Working Women (Tokyo, Japan) in 2002. Dates for residences in the exhibit are 1965, 1975, 1986.
  - Nanasy, Ilona, collection, 1978-2003, Extent: 0.2 cubic feet (Oversize 10.1-10.4)
    Architect of Budapest, Hungary. Began working in 1978 at the Hungarian Ministry of Housing, then opened a private practice in 1991. The collection consists of residential, commercial and competition projects, mostly in Hungary. Inventory available.
  - Newcomb College drawings, 1899, 1915, 1920, Extent: 0.2 cubic feet (Oversize 13)
    Newcomb College, a coordinate college of Tulane University 1886-2006, offered an industrial art program featuring pottery, interior design, furniture making, and many other arts and crafts in an effort to educate women in the "practical side of life" and also to provide employment for women at a time when few opportunities existed. The collection includes 18 original pencil drawings - 5 by Wanda Simmons (c. 1915), 1 by Ora Reams (1911), 1 by Phyllis Evelyn Reeves (c. 1920-1924), and 11 unattributed. See also Fannie Magee drawings, Acc2010-033.
  - Novakova, Zdenka Marie, papers, 1979, 1988-1991 and undated, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 6, Oversize 19)
    Architect and artist of the Czech Republic. Graduated from Prague Technical University in 1963 with a degree in architecture and has designed several architectural projects in the Czech Republic, most notably the interior of a Gothic church in the town of Most. Papers consist of architectural drawings, photographs, a booklet about her work, two exhibit catalogs, and a CD with plans.
  - Nowicki, Stanislawa, papers, 1950, 1953, 2000 and undated, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 6)
    Nowicki's papers consist of a biographical sketch as well as recollections of Nowicki written by student of the School of Architecture at the University of Pennsylvania. There are photographs of the interior and exterior of her house in Villanova, Pennsylvania, and a photograph of a curtain that Nowicki designed for the Coliseum in Raleigh. Inventory available.
  - Okhotina, Nina, papers, 2005 and undated, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 6)
    Born 1927. Architect in Russia. Graduated from Moscow Architecture Institute in 1951. Worked on institutional architectural projects until her retirement in 1983. Now an active painter and artist. Collection contains one exhibit brochure and a draft copy of a book with color illustrations of her architectural projects and photographs of her paintings.
  - Ozkose, Aysun, papers, 2004 and undated, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 6)
    Architect in Turkey. Includes curriculum vitae and articles.
  - Patkau, Patricia, papers, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 6)
    Born in 1950, Winnipeg, Manitoba, Canada. The collection includes a book entitled Patkau Architects and a résumé from the firm that includes an extensive project list. The book is cataloged separately in the Addison library catalog, and is available through the Special Collections Reading Room. Inventory available.
  - Patrulius, Irina, papers, 1998, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 6)
    Architectural historian of Bucharest, Romania. Collection consists of a transcript of a speech given in French by Patrulius about the work of early women architects in Romania, and photographic negatives of the work of Romanian architects Henriette Delavrancea-Gibory (1894-1987), Virginia Haret (1894-1962), and Maria Cotescu (1896- ).
  - Pattison, Harriet, papers, 2004, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 6)
    Harriet Pattison, ASLA, is a landscape architect currently based in Pennsylvania. The collection contains a typed copy of her remarks to a 2004 Yale symposium about her collaboration with architect Louis Kahn as well as photocopied pages showing selected landscape projects she designed.
  - Pavlova, Liudmila Pavlova, papers, 1962-1990, Extent: 2.0 cubic feet (Box 18, Oversize 4)
    Born 1932 in the Rostov Region of Russia. Worked for 35 years (1956-1989) in "Glavproekt" the largest state design organization in Sofia, Bulgaria. She now practices in her private architectural office (dated February 2009). Collection consists of some biographical material and photocopies of several projects including a library, a home, sanitoriums, and office buildings.
  - Pavlova, Radka, architectural drawings, 1964-1999, Extent: 6.7 cu.ft. (Box 18, Oversize 18.1-18.4)
    Born in Bulgaria. Designed interiors and furniture, as well as urban design and landscape. Collection consists of a portfolio, original drawings, resume, clippings and photocopies. The material reflects Pavlova's broad experience, which varies from the design of master plans, urban design, interior design, design of schools, cultural centers, hotels, restaurants, housing, libraries, business centers, commercial centers, etc. The drawings cover several aspects of Pavlova's design activity in different periods. It starts with the project of Park Kenana dated 1964 and ends with the project of the Commercial center in Blagoevgrad designed in 1986 and completed in 1999. Inventory available online.
  - Perriand, Charlotte, biographical material, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 6)
    Born in 1903. Architect and designer that specialized in furniture. Worked with Le Corbusier and Pierre Jeanneret. Biographical article discussing her career.
  - Petrova, Iskra Nikolova, papers, 1981, Extent: 2.0 cubic feet (Oversize 17)
    Iskra Nikolova Petrova studied architecture at Sofia Polytechnic. After her graduation in 1977, she worked for the state design and construction organization "Technoeksportstroi," which built many buildings in Africa and the Near East. The collection contains seven competition project drawings for housing neighborhood in Haarlem / Haarlemmermeer, Nigeria, Africa, ca. 1981, and a two-page curriculum vitae.
  - Pidgeon, Monica, article, 1999, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 6)
    Column from The Architects' Journal titled "People" dated 8 July 1999.
  - Pierce, Marjorie, obituary, 2000, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 6)
    Obituary from The Boston Globe dated January 20, 2000
  - Pietilä, Raili, publications, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 6)
    Architect from Helsinki, Finland who works in collaboration with her husband. The book is titled Modernin Arkkitehtuurin Valimaastoissa or Intermediate Zones in Modern Architecture. Also an article "Pietilä modernin arkkitehtuurin välimaastoissa intermediate zones in modern architecture."
  - Pingel, Gerda, exhibition posters, 1998, Extent: 1.8 cu.ft. (Oversize 25)
    Architect from Germany. Collection consists of exhibition posters and drawings presented at the 12th UIFA Congress, Tokyo, Japan (1998). The drawings detail several buildings on the University of Kiel campus, Pharmacy building, "Sealarium," Research Laboratory, and Auditorium of the College Center and the efforts of the architect to integrate institutional buildings into the surrounding community.
  - Pinos, Carme, booklet, 1995, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 6)
    Born in Barcelona in 1954, Pinos graduated from the Barcelona School of Architecture in 1979. Her papers consist of a booklet, published in 1995 to showcase Pinos' work when she was awarded the Plym Distinguished Professorship in Architecture at the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign in 1994. The booklet contains pictures of Pinos' work and comments from students and colleagues. Inventory available.
  - Plumb, Helga, papers, 1977-1978, 1995, Extent: 3.1 cubic feet (Box 6, Oversize 23)
    Helga Plumb is a retired architect from Toronto, Ontario, and partner of the Dubois Plumb Partnership in Toronto from 1979-1993. The collection includes her curriculum vitae and architectural drawings and sketches of the Tom Longboat Junior School, Toronto, Canada a project that began in 1977. Inventory available.
  - Popova, Rositsa, drawings, 1987-1990, Extent: 3.3 cubic feet (Box 18, Oversize 26.1-26.2)
    Rositsa Peeva-Popova (sister of Maria Peeva) graduated from Sofia Polytechnic in 1981, and was then assigned by the government to work for the Design Organization in the town of Gabrovo. She later worked for towns of Ruse and Schumen before establishing a private practice with her architect husband. That practice opened in Schumen but moved to Varna, where Popova teaches (2007) architecture at the Varna Free University. Popova's work centers on urban design, with many apartment buildings as well as gas stations, commercial facilities, and urban space designs. Her donation includes drawings for an Evangelical Church and a Fashion House for the Factory "Val Poskova," both in Schumen as well as a curriculum vitae.
  - Portugali, Nili, curriculum vitae, 2000, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 6)
    Born in 1948. Architect of Israel. Collection is composed of her curriculum vitae.
  - Praun, Anna-Lulja, papers, 1986-1987, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 6)
    The collection consists of articles about exhibitions of Praun's furniture in the late 1980's. Also included is an exhibition announcement with the picture of the "Komponierpult fur Gyorgy Ligeti," a desk which appears in most of the articles. A photograph of Praun and a book, published in 1986, entitled Anna-Lulja Praun. Inventory available.
  - Prochazka, Elsa, papers, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 6)
    Born 1948. Architect and professor at the University for Applied Arts in Vienna, Austria. Papers consist of lists of her various professional achievements and a brochure of the work she did with the group "Igirien."
  - Rachel, Shalit, drawings and curriculum vitae, 1993, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 11)
    Born 1919, Transylvania. Attended Sorbonne 1938-1939; she received her diploma in 1950 in architectural engineering from Transylvania Polytechnic. After ten years as a designed at the Design Institute in Bucharest, she moved to Israel where her design work focused on governmental institutions and offices. She taught in both high schools and professional schools and has worked on developing new materials for architectural uses. The collection consists of architectural sketches of some Rachel's work including an opera house, Complex for Winter Olympiada, Indian Museum. Inventory available.
  - Reese, Ilse Meissner, papers, 1999, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 18)
    Ilse Meissner Reese came to the United States from Germany in 1938. She received a certificate in Industrial Design (1941) and a Bachelor of Architecture (1946) from the Pratt Institute, Brooklyn, New York. She spent ten years as an Associate Editor of Progressive Architecture (1955-1965) before going into private practice in 1975. The collection includes one folder of biographical material containing a summary of Reese's educational and professional experience from 1941-1999 and a statement by Reese entitled "Reflections on a Career in Architecture."
  - Ribarova, Elisaveta, papers, 1987-1993, Extent: 2.1 cubic feet (Box 6, Oversize 11)
    Born 1939. Bulgarian architect. Collection includes a résumé and several drawings. The drawings consist of a residential building, competition project for "St. Visarion" cathedral, and a project for the National Lyceum for Antique Langues and Culture in Sofia, Bulgaria.
  - Riggs, Lutah Marie, photographs, 1958, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 6)
    1896-1984. The collection consists of color prints and slides of the Vedanta Temple in Montecito, California. Considered one of Santa Barbara's most important historic architects, Riggs's work is in the Architecture & Design Collection, University Art Museum, University of California at Santa Barbara. Inventory available.
  - Robertson, Donna, papers, 1980, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 11)
    Donna Robertson has served as the dean of Tulane University's School of Architecture and the Dean of the Illinois Institute of Technology, College of Architecture. She received a Master of Architecture degree from the University of Virginia School of Architecture in 1978. The collection consists of her ink and pencil drawings, and a plan as well as an exterior elevation of the Bessie Smith Memorial Dance Hall. Inventory available.
  - Rueschemeyer, Marilyn, publication, 1993, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 6)
    Born 1938. Sociologist and head of the Department of History, Philosophy, and the Social Sciences at the Rhode Island School of Design. Has written on topics about residential communities in eastern Europe, particularly the former German Democratic Republic. Collection consists of a reprint of an article written by Rueschemeyer for Urban Studies (Vol. 30, no. 3, 1993) entitled "East Germany's New Towns in Transition: A Grassroots View of the Impact of Unification."
  - Rysdale, Anne J. (1920-2017), Pattern Book, c.1950, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 18)
    Anne Rysdale (1920-2017), also known as Barbara N. Rysdale, was the only practicing female architect in the state of Arizona between 1949-1960. She was born and raised in Tucson. She graduated from the University of Arizona in 1940 with a degree in Engineering and Fine Arts as the University of Arizona did not have an architecture program at that time. In 1946, she received her Master's of Architecture at the University of Washington (Seattle). In her early career, she worked for Henry Jaastad and Arthur Brown, two prominent Tucson architects. She established her own firm Anne J. Rysdale, Architect & Assocs, Inc. in 1949. Rysdale Associates grew to be a 105 person architectural and construction management firm with offices in Tucson and Scottsdale, Arizona and Albuquerque, New Mexico. Rysdale began practicing architecture in Florida in 1981. The collection contains a pattern book titled Anne J. Rysdale Distinctive Plans for Western Homes & Multi-Units. The book is divided into six sections: one bedroom (4); two bedroom (76); three bedroom (72); four bedroom (17); duplex (12); and triplex (4).
  - Sachs, Lisbeth papers, 1988, 1993-1996, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 6)
    Born 1914. Architect of Zurich, Switzerland. Papers include photographs of designs and structures by Sachs, and a copy of Zum Entwurf Des Kurtheaters Baden Von Lisbeth Sachs by Matthias Bram, about Sachs' design of theaters. Also includes a reprint from a publication of the contributions to a colloquium, "Building with Intelligence," in which Sachs gave a paper, "What Do We Mean by Intelligence: Intelligence and Vision in Building," in November 1993 in Stuttgart, Germany.
  - Sankalia, Hema. curriculum vitae, 1992, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 6)
    Curriculum vita 1992.
  - Santos, Alda, biographical material, 1985, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 6)
    Born 1945. City architect of Porto, Portugal. Papers include an autobiographical sketch and a 1985 article about Santos.
  - Sarantsatsral, Ochirpurev, papers, 2001, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 6, Box 14)
    Architect of Mongolia and IAWA Board member. The collection includes the magazine Mongolian Construction, which features a shopping center by Sarantsatsral and photographs of the project, as well as a photo of a model of a restaurant and photocopies of a master plan of a monastery. In 2003, CAD architectural plans for a building designed by Sarantsatsral and her son were added. Inventory available.
  - Scarlette, Shannon Taylor, papers, Extent: 0.3 cubic feet (Box 7, Oversize 14)
    Principal of Shannon Taylor Scarlett, Architects, of Boston, Massachusetts, since 1991. Won first prize in a design competition for a library and civic center in Blacksburg, Virginia, in 1992. Papers consist of curriculum vitae, a firm history, a description of the Blacksburg library and civic center design, and the competition entry boards.
  - Schmidt-Kirchberg, Barbara, papers, 1990, 1999, and undated, Extent: 1.5 cubic feet (Box 7, Oversize 4)
    Born 1936. Architect of Munster, Germany, and Professor of Design and Interior Design at the Professional University in Munster. Papers consist of a reprint of an article from the journal Deutsche Bauzeitung about a project she designed, curriculum vitae, brochure for her lecture, "Light Space," and two oversize posters titled "Modesty and Reflexion: A little town and the new informatic needs."
  - Schmidt-Thomsen, Helga, papers, 1960-1969 and undated, Extent: 3.0 cubic feet (Box 7, Oversize 24)
    Born 1938. Architect of Berlin, Germany, and former member of the IAWA Board of Advisors. Papers consist of twenty-nine architectural drawings for three designs done while a student in the 1960s at the Technical University of Berlin, where she earned her architecture degree. The projects include a design for the Goethe Institute in Berlin; the Pflanzenhaus and Palmengarten, or botanical garden, in Frankfurt; and a student competition for a playground building in which she won first prize. Also includes a presentation, "The Collaboration of Couples in Architecture," given by Schmidt-Thomsen in San Francisco in 1987, and biographical information.
  - Schütte-Lihotzky, Margarete, exhibition announcements, 1993, 1997, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 7)
  - Scott Brown, Denise, biographical material, 1984-1985, 2013 and undated, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 7)
    Architect and planner, principal of the firm Venturi, Scott Brown and Associates. Collection contains biographical information about Scott Brown and the firm Venturi, Rauch and Scott Brown.
  - Seifen, Barbara, thesis, 1984, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 7)
    Architect of Hannover, Germany. Materials include a photograph of Seifen and a copy of her thesis from the University of Hannover, Aber Vorbilder Hat Es Keine Gegeben: Erfahrungen Von Architektinnen Im Beruf (But There Were No Role Models: Experiences of Women Architects in their Profession).
  - Seixas, Maria Fernanda Machado, curriculum vitae, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 7)
    Architect of Porto, Portugal. Curriculum vitae.
  - Sepic, Liljana, papers, 2005 and undated, Extent: 0.1 cu.ft. (Box 20)
    Faculty of Architecture, University of Zagreb, Croatia (2011). Papers include an article "Housing reconstruction of war damaged towns and villages in eastern Croatia" (2005) and photographs and 1 drawing for an optician shop in Zagreb. Material is in English.
  - Shackelford, Grace, drawings, 1962-1965 and undated, Extent: 10.0 cubic feet (Oversize 3.1-3.4)
    Designer formerly of Blacksburg, Virginia. Collection consists of architectural drawings for three residences in Blacksburg, Montgomery County, and Woolwine, Virginia, that Shackelford designed or remodeled.
  - Shayo, Anna, papers, 1991-1992 and undated, Extent: 1.6 cubic feet (Box 14, Box 18)
    Born 1957. Architect with the Capital Development Authority of Dodoma, Tanzania. Papers include a curriculum vitae, reports, and architectural drawings by Shayo and others about shelters in Africa and the DOVAP House Construction Project done by Shayo for the Netherlands Development Organization and Municipal Council of Dodoma.
  - Simon, Cathy J., biographical material, 1983-1991, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 7)
    A founding principal and Director of Architecture for Simon Martin-Vegue Winkelstein Moris, an architecture firm in San Francisco, California. Formerly a partner (1978-1985) with Marquis Associates in San Francisco. Founding member of the Organization of Women Architects and Design Professionals and former lecturer at the College of Environmental Design of the University of California, Berkeley (1973-1985). Fellow of the American Institute of Architects. Projects include the San Francisco Main Library, the Newport Beach (California) Central Library, the San Francisco Day School, and the Primate Discovery Center at the San Francisco Zoo. Papers include a curriculum vitae, detailed brochures on most of her projects, and reprints of articles from Architectural Record, The New York Times, and Architecture, about Simon's designs.
  - Sion, Maria Militza, papers, 1967-1999, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 7, Oversize 6)
    Architect and artist in Romania. Papers include her résumé, a company dossier, photographs and photocopies of portions of her work showing projects such as Imobil Locuinte and a residential building in Bucharest, art work and correspondence. Inventory available.
  - Sklarek, Norma, biographical material, 1987 and undated, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 18)
    Born 1928. Architect of Los Angeles, California, and the first African-American woman to become a licensed architect in New York (1954) and California (1962), and a Fellow of the American Institute of Architects. Principal of the Jerde Partnership in Los Angeles and director of the Los Angeles chapter of the AIA. Materials include a curriculum vitae, a reprint of an article, "Designing Women," from The California Executive, (November 1987) and photographs of and information about several of her designs in California.
  - Slunkova, Inessa Nikolaevina, biographical information, 2002 and undated, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 7)
    Russian architectural historian. Collection includes two photographs and biographical information. Also included in the donation are four published volumes about Russian architecture. Book topics include religious buildings, Russian manor houses, and Russian monasteries. Books are cataloged in Addison and located in the Rare Book Room.
  - Smith, Cloethiel Woodard, obituary, 1993, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 7)
    Architect that worked primarily in Washington, D.C.. Materials include two obituaries from 1993.
  - Smithson, Alison, drawings, 1982, Extent: 1.75 cubic feet (Oversize 5)